const e="We could not find what you asked for, but got you this",a="civiledu",o=200,t=120,i=[{id:24,question:"The nearest government to the people and an important means of promoting grassroots development is the",option:{a:"state government",b:"unitary government",c:"local government",d:"federal government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:350,question:"The administrative class in the public service is to",option:{a:"implement policies",b:"formulate policies",c:"veto policies",d:"oversee policies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:405,question:"A major way of promoting responsible parenthood is through",option:{a:"sex education",b:"sound education",c:"population control measures",d:"tax reduction measures"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:41,question:"One of the major barriers to national development is the",option:{a:"low poverty level",b:"existence of multi - party system",c:"prevalence of corrupt practices",d:"persistent rural - urban migration"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:109,question:"Punishment for law breaking include the following except ..........",option:{a:"freedom of movement",b:"detention",c:"sanctions",d:"political instability"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:78,question:"Public Complaints Commission in Nigeria is also known as",option:{a:"elder’s forum.",b:"judiciary.",c:"ombudsman.",d:"people’s court."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:293,question:"The followings are symptoms of Ebola excepts",option:{a:"sudden fever and vomiting",b:"headaches and diarrhea",c:"muscle pains",d:"frequent hunger and increase thirst for water"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:252,question:"Ejiro, who is not sick decide to take the same drug for the same duration as recommended for Omonigho by the doctor.Ejiro’s action can be described as a form of",option:{a:"preventive measure",b:"drug abuse",c:"drug trafficking",d:"Self help activity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:386,question:"Based on the above story, which of the following would Dr.Fajir not be allowed to do while in prison?",option:{a:"Voting during elections",b:"Engaging in hard labour",c:"Participating in prison fellowship",d:"Writing examination"},section:"Dr. Fajir was the Minister of Works and Urban Development in the Gambia Republic. As such, he was entrusted with the public fund so that his ministry could construct new roads and rehabilitate the existing ones. Unfortunately. Dr Fajir embezzled the money entrusted in his care and siphoned same to his foreign accounts. This led to the deplorable conditions of roads in the Republic. The Crime Commission arrested and prosecuted him accordingly. Subsequently, he was given the opportunity to be defended by lawyers of his choice in a Court of Law. However, he was found guilty and sentenced to 15 years imprisonment with hard labour without the option of a fine. In addition, he forfeited all his ill-gotten wealth to the Republic.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:401,question:"An ideology that aims at promoting national consciousness and identity is",option:{a:"nationalism",b:"socialization",c:"civic culture",d:"progressivism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:319,question:"The three larges and most influential ethnic groups in Nigeria are",option:{a:"Yoruba, Edo and Hausa",b:"Igbo, Iteskiri and Hausa",c:"Hausa, Igbo and Yoruba",d:"Fulani, Yoruba and Efik"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:194,question:"Decrees are laws made by ............",option:{a:"Democratic government",b:"The prime minister",c:"The military",d:"Parliaments"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:408,question:"Which of the following is not a function of the National Drug Law Enforcement Agency (NDLEA)?",option:{a:"Applying and implementing all drug laws",b:"Arresting, investigating and prosecuting drug traffickers",c:"Undertaking the registration of companies dealing 	in drugs",d:"Carrying out enlightenment campaigns on drug trafficking"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:161,question:"Law made by military governments are called",option:{a:"decrees",b:"Bye-laws",c:"Edicts",d:"acts"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:149,question:"The commission charged with the conduct of federal 	elections in Nigeria between 2014 and 2015 is..........",option:{a:"Nec",b:"fedeco",c:"Inec",d:"Necon"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:156,question:"Workers in the Public Corporations are known as",option:{a:"Civil servants",b:"Private employees",c:"Public servants",d:"Professional employees"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:379,question:"The motherland in the monologue could best be described as",option:{a:"a nation in transition",b:"a morally upgrading country",c:"a socially viable nation",d:"an ethically bankrupt country"},section:"Oh Motherland, you were a precious country, a beacon of hope and aspiration as well as toga of pride of your citizens at independence. However, today you are bedeviled with evil, engulfed in darkness and to say the obvious, at the edge of total moral collapse. Corruption, fraud, deception and dishonesty are prevalent; drug peddlers are having a field day. In schools and colleges, radicalism, prostitution, cultism, examination malpractice among other social vices are order of the day.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:162,question:"The ultimate aim of political parties is to",option:{a:"implement people oriented programmes",b:"acquire and exercise power",c:"increase the political awareness of the electorate",d:"formulate and implement policies"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:127,question:"One of the following is not human right group",option:{a:"Constitutional Right Project (CRP)",b:"National Association of Democratic Lawyers (NADL)",c:"Nigeria Bar Association (NBA)",d:"Civil Liberties Organization (CLO)"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:349,question:"Which of the following instruments is not used by a civil society group?",option:{a:"Propaganda",b:"Boycott",c:"Protest",d:"Violence"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:27,question:"Which of the following is not necessary for public servants to perform effectively?",option:{a:"In - service training",b:"Appointment based on nepotism",c:"Value re - orientation for public servants",d:"Incentives for meeting set goals"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:366,question:"Which of the following is not a means of reducing the incidence of HIV/AIDS in our society?",option:{a:"Education and enlightenment programs",b:"The use of specially designed cutlery by victims",c:"Avoiding pre-marital and extra-marital sex",d:"Upholding the value of chastity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:301,question:"An individual with feverish condition who has taken Panadol is advised to see the ............ if the feverish condition persists after .......... days",option:{a:"father, four",b:"pastor, three",c:"doctor, three",d:"doctor, ten"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:102,question:"There are ............. local government in Nigeria",option:{a:"700",b:"714",c:"744",d:"774"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:104,question:"Television and radio are example  of ......... media",option:{a:"print",b:"electronic",c:"advertising",d:"mass"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:187,question:"The following are ways to prevent drug addiction except",option:{a:"civic education",b:"law enforcement and regulation",c:"mass media effort",d:"voting at election"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:131,question:"The organization with the motives and goals of helping people is called",option:{a:"social group",b:"charity group",c:"pressure group",d:"human right group"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:356,question:"Which of the following statements is not correct?",option:{a:"Valid driver’s license must be obtained before attempting to drive",b:"Flowing garment can be worn on a motorcycle or bicycle",c:"Headlights should be used during unfavourable weather",d:"Drivers must not engage in distractive activities while driving"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:36,question:"From this dialogue, it is very likely that Wanja will be exhibiting the following characters except",option:{a:"disobedience to constituted authority",b:"truancy and perpetual lateness to school",c:"hospitable attitude towards people",d:"arrogance and unruly behaviour."},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:383,question:"Which of the following can not be easily abused?",option:{a:"Cosmetics",b:"Stimulant",c:"Tobacco",d:"Narcotics"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:132,question:"The following are the reasons why people do not participate in polities except",option:{a:"illiteracy",b:"lack of justice",c:"multi-party system",d:"religion"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:114,question:"Cocaine, morphine and heroin are example of",option:{a:"tobacco",b:"steroids",c:"narcotics",d:"inhalants"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:130,question:"One of the following is a social group",option:{a:"dangote group of companies",b:"rotary club",c:"Millan group",d:"human right Africa"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:213,question:"The exercise of arbitrary power, whims and caprices constitutes a negation of .........",option:{a:"rule of law",b:"fundamental human right",c:"checks and balance",d:"indirect rule"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:165,question:"One of the main duties of the local government service commission is to",option:{a:"supervise and manage the personnel of local government",b:"conduct election into local council",c:"create an enabling working environment for council workers",d:"handle request for the creation of more local government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:254,question:"The Ebola virus sneaked into Nigeria through",option:{a:"The Liberian born American, Mr Patrick Sawyer",b:"The Ghanaian born American, Mr Patrick Sayer",c:"Members of the Boko Haram",d:"Monkeys and bats"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:93,question:"The public Service is a branch of the ____ arm of government",option:{a:"civilian",b:"executive",c:"judiciary",d:"legislative"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:143,question:"Motorcyclists must always protect their heads with safety ............. which must be properly fastened",option:{a:"seat belt",b:"head guild",c:"helmets",d:"cap cycles"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:163,question:"The main objective of pressure groups is to",option:{a:"promote the interest of political parties",b:"influence legislation for the benefit of their member",c:"protect the interest of the country against foreigners",d:"serve as opposition to the government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:16,question:"The division of Nigeria into various constituencies with each electing a person to represent it in the National Assembly is a demonstration of",option:{a:"checks and balances",b:"popular participation",c:"political rivalry among the constituents",d:"drive towards secession in the country."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:170,question:"Which of these countries operate a unitary system of 	government",option:{a:"Nigeria",b:"U. S. A",c:"Ghana",d:"Britain"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:42,question:"The quotation above shows that the speaker is concerned about",option:{a:"nationalism",b:"revolution",c:"tourism",d:"welfarism"},section:"“Here is your country. Cherish these natural wonders, cherish the natural resources, cherish the history and romance as sacred heritage, for your children and your children’s children. Do not let selfish men or greedy interests skin your country of its beauty, its riches...”",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:38,question:"From Ada’s admonition, it could be deduced that taking hard drugs could",option:{a:"make people respect the addicts.",b:"lead to insanity of the addicts",c:"make people to adore the drug addicts",d:"ensure courteous behaviour by the addicts"},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:99,question:"................ is the apex body saddled by law to fight corruption and other related offences",option:{a:"IRS",b:"ICPC",c:"EFCC",d:"NPF"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:290,question:"Which of these categories of people stand the greatest risk of contacting the Ebola virus .........",option:{a:"Lecturers and students in the school",b:"Health workers and their family members",c:"Hunters and their family members",d:"b and c above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:116,question:"Cannabis is also called .........",option:{a:"barbiturates",b:"cassava",c:"marijuana",d:"caffeine"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:84,question:"Which of the following is not a function of political parties?",option:{a:"Aggregation of opinion",b:"Educating the government",c:"Interest articulation",d:"Unifying factor."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:278,question:"Which of the following is not the civic obligation of a citizen",option:{a:"payment of taxes",b:"freedom of conscience and speech",c:"voting during elections",d:"obedience to law"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:94,question:"When the national flag is flown half mask, it is a sign of national",option:{a:"centenary celebration",b:"children’s day",c:"independence",d:"mourning"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:120,question:"One of the following is a cause of single parents in Nigeria",option:{a:"slow parenting",b:"social group",c:"nature of work",d:"divorce"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:284,question:"Government is the machinery established to manage the affairs of",option:{a:"the state",b:"the civil service",c:"peasants and students",d:"strangers"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:3,question:"A major characteristic of civil society is",option:{a:"the desire to win election",b:"corporate responsibility",c:"social responsibility",d:"political gerrymandering."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:8,question:"Based on the statements above, the decision of the student on having a bullet proof vest shows that cultism",option:{a:"spreads fear and terror.",b:"is a training ground for armed forces.",c:"breeds courageous graduates.",d:"propagates self - defence."},section:"NEWS: ‘Rival Cult Group Killed Ten on Campus’<br> 	STUDENT: I will definitely need a bullet proof vest before I can go back to the Campus.<br>",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:315,question:"One way for Nigerians to maintain steady good health is by",option:{a:"taking malaria medicine everyday",b:"bathing with salt water and eating bitter kola always",c:"taking balance diet and engaging in regular physical exercise",d:"taking alcohol and cigarettes regularly"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:327,question:"A Taxi diver who mistakenly Jams and kills someone is guilty of ............... and he will receive ................ punishment than if it were a case of ........",option:{a:"murder, less, manslaughter",b:"man slaughter, less, murder",c:"manslaughter, more, murder",d:"civil offence, less, murder"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:9,question:"It could be inferred from the statements above that cultism in schools could lead to",option:{a:"sudden prosperity.",b:"uninterrupted academic calender.",c:"popularity on campus.",d:"untimely death."},section:"NEWS: ‘Rival Cult Group Killed Ten on Campus’<br> 	STUDENT: I will definitely need a bullet proof vest before I can go back to the Campus.<br>",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:77,question:"One advantage of Bi-cameral legislature is that it",option:{a:"guards against intra-party clashes.",b:"is the only system available.",c:"prevents arbitrary law making",d:"projects party manifestoes."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:210,question:"For which of these can someone be arrested while driving on a high way",option:{a:"driving and laughing",b:"driving and singing",c:"driving and eating or receiving phone call",d:"driving and crying"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:256,question:"Malaria fever can be transmitted through",option:{a:"hand shaking",b:"eating of unbalanced diet",c:"mosquito bite",d:"eating of bush meat such as bat and monkey"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:190,question:"The function of Federal Road Safety Corp (FRSC) is",option:{a:"Enforcing the traffic regulation on road",b:"making law",c:"executing law",d:"Interpreting law"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:186,question:"The lack of interest in politics by many citizens in a country is called",option:{a:"civic agitation",b:"mass apathy",c:"mass protest",d:"political unrest"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:374,question:"Civil Society groups perform the following roles during general elections except",option:{a:"educating the voters",b:"serving as watchdog",c:"counting votes",d:"stimulating participation"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:257,question:"Plenty of money in the society, not backed by commensurate productive activities can lead to",option:{a:"deflation",b:"inflation",c:"National developmental",d:"cashless society"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:375,question:"Which of the following is not an example of civil society group?",option:{a:"United Action for Democracy",b:"United Nations Organization",c:"Transition Monitoring Group",d:"Amnesty International"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:123,question:"The clause which exempts the president from being prosecuted while still in office is called",option:{a:"military clause",b:"special clause",c:"conviction clause",d:"immunity clause"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:309,question:"The Ebola virus can be prevented by",option:{a:"washing our hands regularly and applying sanitizer",b:"washing our head always",c:"taking drugs regularly",d:"eating balanced diet"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:353,question:"Naturalized citizens cannot be denied their legal status as members of a country unless if they",option:{a:"are jailed for one year within seven years of acquiring citizenship",b:"are found guilty to be spies or secret agents for another country",c:"refuse to represent the country in an international sporting event",d:"give adequate information to the host country"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:249,question:"Ejiro, the senior brother of Omonigho had fever last week. The doctor prescribed a certain drug for him, He was asked to take one tablet, three times a day for four days. He took the drug as recommend for the first and second day and stopped. Five days later he took one tablet in the morning and one again at night. Omonigho’s action can be said to be a kind of",option:{a:"bad drug administration",b:"drug Abuse",c:"drug trafficking",d:"Human trafficking"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:416,question:"HIV/AIDS is generally described as terminal in nature because it is",option:{a:"preventable",b:"transmittable",c:"avertable",d:"incurable"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:157,question:"Membership of a society is",option:{a:"conventional",b:"Mandatory",c:"Voluntary",d:"Constitutional"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:369,question:"Democracy thrives most where there is",option:{a:"nonpartisan judiciary",b:"freedom of speech and association",c:"absence of universal suffrage",d:"one-party system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:267,question:"The right practice of democracy can",option:{a:"ensure equity, justice and far play",b:"discourage political education and awareness’",c:"political unrest",d:"lawlessness"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:322,question:"General Murtala Mohammed was assassinated on his way to work in ..............",option:{a:"February 13, 1976",b:"June 12, 1993",c:"October 1, 1960",d:"June 8, 1998"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:368,question:"The Supreme Court of Nigeria helps in law",option:{a:"drafting",b:"application",c:"interpretation",d:"enforcement"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:193,question:"Which of these is a type of parenthood",option:{a:"single parenthood",b:"ethnic parenthood",c:"village parenthood",d:"clan parenthood"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:392,question:"Two forms of road signs are regulatory and",option:{a:"punitive",b:"informative",c:"persuasive",d:"inhibitive"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:266,question:"If you were to be in the Governor’s shoes which of the following would you have chosen?",option:{a:"Miranda and seven up",b:"coca cola and Fanta",c:"petroleum",d:"stock, bonds and cash"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:237,question:"Popular participation refers to",option:{a:"Political Apathy",b:"The active involvement of citizens in the social political activities of a country",c:"The rule of the party with the largest number of supporters",d:"The rule of a prominent and popular politician"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:212,question:"The armed forces and the police are part of the ........ organ of government",option:{a:"executive",b:"judicial",c:"legislative",d:"informative"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:251,question:"If Omonigho had taken the tablet one three times a day for six days his action constitutes a kind of",option:{a:"good drug administration",b:"drug abuse",c:"drug trafficking",d:"none of the abuse"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:133,question:"............... is the prejudicial treatment of fellow human being",option:{a:"god fatherism",b:"independence",c:"justice",d:"discrimination"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:373,question:"Which of the following is not a form of political participation?",option:{a:"Taking part in voters’ registration exercise",b:"Voting during elections",c:"Joining political party",d:"Ballot box stuffing during elections"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:355,question:"Which of the following is not an example of orderliness?",option:{a:"Listening skill",b:"Driving skill",c:"Decorum",d:"Deviance"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:231,question:"Which of these characteristics of the civil service ensure continuity of government?",option:{a:"Neutrality",b:"Permanence",c:"Bureaucracy",d:"Loyalty"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:22,question:"Conflicts are better resolved in the society through",option:{a:"tribunal",b:"litigation.",c:"dialogue",d:"the court"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:338,question:"On the 18th of November 2014 in Yobe, some crowds lynched a suspected suicide bomber. The action of the crowd is .....",option:{a:"right because ‘he who kills by the sword must die by the sword’",b:"wrong because they have unlawfully taken the law into their hands, they should have handed the suicide  bomber over to the police",c:"right because we all have to fights against all forms of terrorism",d:"right so that others will learn lesson from this action"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:142,question:"From the basic road traffic regulation pedestrians should not attempt to cross the road when the light are ............. and ...............",option:{a:"green and yellow",b:"green and red",c:"yellow and red",d:"red and yellow"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:429,question:"Democracy is yet to take firm root in Africa because",option:{a:"it retards African development",b:"African leaders are not experienced enough",c:"most African leaders detest the will of the people",d:"it is an expensive system of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:61,question:"In democracy, lack of press freedom leads to the denial of freedom of",option:{a:"association",b:"expression",c:"movement",d:"voting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:297,question:"HIV and Ebola can be contacted through contact with",option:{a:"Non infected person",b:"contaminated medical equipment such as needles and syringes",c:"Very sick person",d:"Healthy reptiles"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:325,question:"A committee of PDP members is made up of 9 Hausas, 8 Igbo and 7 Yorubas. If the president wishes to choose just one person to be his special adviser, find the probability that the person chosen is neither Hausa nor Yoruba",option:{a:"7/24",b:"2/3",c:"3/8",d:"1/3"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:5,question:"Human Rights are basic natural rights which people enjoy primarily because they are",option:{a:"members of a political party",b:"international citizens",c:"members of a community",d:"human beings."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:136,question:"The process whereby an individual choose to favour a person who come from his family or tribe over other people or tribes is known as",option:{a:"stereotype",b:"ethnicity",c:"nepotism",d:"favouritism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:18,question:"The principle that public servants cannot be held responsible for their official actions denotes",option:{a:"impartiality",b:"accountability",c:"anonymity",d:"neutrality."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:230,question:"What is the minimum age for voters in Nigeria",option:{a:"15",b:"20",c:"18",d:"50"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:259,question:"The primary duty of the army is to",option:{a:"execute the law",b:"interpret the law",c:"overthrow the government when there is anarchy",d:"defend the country against external aggression"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:430,question:"Nationalism ensures the following except",option:{a:"national consciousness",b:"secession in a country",c:"national integration",d:"unity in a country"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:362,question:"A major factor responsible for human trafficking is",option:{a:"hunger",b:"illiteracy",c:"greed",d:"joblessness"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:339,question:"In the year 2014 the catholic church in Nigeria suspended the usual hand shaking (as a sign of peace) among its members just after the “Lord’s prayer” The most likely reason for this action is to prevent the 		spread of ............, in case a member has it",option:{a:"HIV/AIDs virus",b:"The Ebola virus",c:"Evil and demonic spirit",d:"malaria fever"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:217,question:"An important characteristics of Democracy is",option:{a:"The absence of free press and mass media",b:"Unequal political rights",c:"Respect for principle of rule of law",d:"The absence of separation of powers between the   arms and levels of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:265,question:"Some years ago a popular Governor in one of the states in Nigeria was asked to mention some mineral 	resources from his state. He made mention of “Fanta, Pepsi, Coca cola. The governor is",option:{a:"right",b:"wrong",c:"illiterate",d:"unpatriotic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:205,question:"Nigeria became independent in ........... and a Republic in ................ Respectively",option:{a:"1963 and 1960",b:"1960 and 1963",c:"1954 and 1960",d:"None of the above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:206,question:"The process of enlightening or training citizens on their rights and responsibilities is known as",option:{a:"Workshop training",b:"Citizenship Education",c:"Political Education",d:"Citizenship Rights"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:380,question:"In spite of the state of affairs reflected in the above monologue, the citizens can make the country better by being committed to",option:{a:"promoting inter-communal relations",b:"strengthening capacity building",c:"championing moral values",d:"encouraging interpersonal relations"},section:"Oh Motherland, you were a precious country, a beacon of hope and aspiration as well as toga of pride of your citizens at independence. However, today you are bedeviled with evil, engulfed in darkness and to say the obvious, at the edge of total moral collapse. Corruption, fraud, deception and dishonesty are prevalent; drug peddlers are having a field day. In schools and colleges, radicalism, prostitution, cultism, examination malpractice among other social vices are order of the day.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:215,question:"Which of the following can cause Human Trafficking in a country",option:{a:"poverty, youth unemployment and greed",b:"Sound education and proper counselling",c:"Social and economic contentment",d:"B and C above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:10,question:"Victims of human trafficking are usually compelled to engage in",option:{a:"lucrative employment",b:"visiting tourist sites",c:"part - time studies",d:"forced labour."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:89,question:"One of the major problems facing local government administration in Nigeria is",option:{a:"insufficient councilors",b:"lack of control by the central government",c:"lack of funds",d:"leadership"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:394,question:"The following cadre of students are the main target for campus cult membership except",option:{a:"students from wealthy homes",b:"students from influential parents",c:"bold and morally sound students",d:"wayward and fun-loving students"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:121,question:".......... strengthens the sensitive mental and emotional bond between the parent and children",option:{a:"narcissistic parenting",b:"attachment parenting",c:"positive parenting",d:"teenage parenting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:71,question:"The laws made by the third tier of government in Nigeria are refer to as",option:{a:"bye-laws.",b:"constitutional laws.",c:"decrees.",d:"edicts"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:337,question:"Some years to come, when you become the President of Nigeria, which of the options below will you choose 	to eradicate porzverty in the country",option:{a:"carry all the poor people away from Nigeria to another country so when there are no poor people poverty will be gone forever",b:"print plenty Naira Notes and give millions to every Nigeria",c:"Import plenty Agricultural and Manufactured goods",d:"None of the above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:270,question:"During a particular voting exercise if majority of the 	people refuse to vote, this can be described as",option:{a:"political stubbornness",b:"political apathy",c:"political awareness",d:"political socialization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:138,question:"Traffic lights are also known and referred to as",option:{a:"three directives light",b:"spotlight",c:"flow traffic directive",d:"informative sign"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:87,question:"One of the following is a country as well as a continent.",option:{a:"Africa",b:"Antarctica",c:"Asia",d:"Australia"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:428,question:"Which of the following is a major challenge to civil society in Nigeria?",option:{a:"Value disorientation",b:"Diverse political interests",c:"Inadequate funding",d:"Unstable political system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:310,question:"If six political parties contest for an election (A, B, C, D, E, F), what is the probability that party C will wine the election",option:{a:"1/3",b:"1/4",c:"1/6",d:"1/2"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:323,question:"Naira and Kobo was introduced in Nigeria in ..............",option:{a:"2nd July,1963",b:"1st January 1972",c:"June 12, 1993",d:"March13, 1995"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:268,question:"Political Apathy can lead to",option:{a:"very fast pace of development",b:"the emergence of sound democratic government",c:"wrong set of people coming into power",d:"development of sound political culture"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:19,question:"Universal Declaration of Human Rights (UDHR) is based on the resolution of the",option:{a:"Human Rights Watch",b:"United Nations Organization",c:"Amnesty International",d:"League of Nations."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:95,question:"One of the ways to ensure a free and fair election is to",option:{a:"allow parties to campaign on election day",b:"appoint a politician as the chairman of the electoral commission",c:"ensure INEC chairman is appointed from a pressure group",d:"guarantee the security of electoral officers and materials"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"}],n={message:e,subject:a,status:200,total:120,data:i};export{i as data,n as default,e as message,o as status,a as subject,t as total};
